<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Game-theory | Kutup]]></title>
  <link href="http://taylansengul.github.io/blog/categories/game-theory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://taylansengul.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-22T14:46:37-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://taylansengul.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Taylan Sengul]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Much Would You Pay to Play This Game?]]></title>
    <link href="http://taylansengul.github.io/blog/2013/12/28/how-much-would-you-pay-to-play-this-game/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-28T06:59:56-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://taylansengul.github.io/blog/2013/12/28/how-much-would-you-pay-to-play-this-game</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="problem">Problem</h2>
<p>Consider the following game. You are playing a die game where you gain x dollars if the result of the rolled die turns out to be x. If you do not like the outcome, you are given a second try and if you do not like the outcome of the second try, you are given a third try. How much would you pay to play this game?</p>

<h2 id="solution">Solution</h2>
<p>As a rational person, you are willing to pay anything less than your expected gain to play this game. And your expected gain depends on your strategy. So first, let’s find the best possible strategy for this game.</p>

<p>If you are in your last try, then you have no choice but to accept the outcome. In this case, your expected gain is $3.5 (\( 3.5 = 1\times \frac{1}{6} + \cdots 6 \times \frac{1}{6}\)). So in your second try, you should only accept a 4, 5 or 6. Because they all beat your expected earning in your last try. So with this best strategy at second try, our expectation is $3.5 if the outcome is 1, 2, 3 and $x if x is 4, 5, 6. This yields an expected gain of
\[
4.25 = 3.5 \times \frac{1}{2} + 4 \times \frac{1}{6} + 5 \times \frac{1}{6} + 6 \times \frac{1}{6} = 1.75 + 2.5
\]
in dollars. Hence in your first try, you should only accept a 5 or 6; accepting anything less than your expected gain ($4.25) is meaningless.</p>

<p>So let’s summarize the best strategy: in your first try, only accept 5 or 6. In your second try, only accept 4, 5 or 6. You have no choice for the third try. With this strategy, your expectation is $4.25 if the first die is 1, 2, 3 or 4 and $x if x is 5 or 6. Thus the expectation of the best strategy in dollars is
\[
4.25 \times \frac{4}{6} + 5 \times \frac{1}{6} + 6 \times \frac{1}{6} = 4.67.
\]</p>

<p>Thus you should agree to pay anything less than $4.67 to play this game.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
